Tatiana Semenova Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Tatiana Semenova Papers
1920-1996
Semenova, Tatiana
During Tatiana Semenova's long career as a ballet dancer and teacher, she danced with the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo and the Paris Opera Ballet, led the American Youth Ballet in Houston, served as Director of the Houston Ballet Academy, and formed the Ballet of Houston. Her collection includes scrapbooks, photograph, programs, and personal materials.
7 boxes; 2.9 linear feet
uhstse01
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Tatiana Semenova was born in St. Petersburg, Russia on July 17, 1920. She moved with her family to Paris when she was five. At the age of seven she began studying at the dancing school of Matilda Kchessinska, a legendary Russian ballerina and wife of Grand Duke Andrei of Russia.
Madame Semenova made her stage debut when she was eleven with a Russian opera company formed in London by Sir Thomas Beecham. The following year she began her formal dance career as a member of the Col. Vassili de Basil's famed Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, touring the United States and South America. In 1937 Semenova joined the Paris Opera Ballet as premiere danseuse starring in stage entertainments with Lucien Boyer, Sascha Guitry, Maurice Chevalier and Charles Trenet.
During World War II, in coordination with the United Service Organizations (USO), Semonova formed a group called the Foxhole Ballet to tour Europe and Africa. While performing in Rome on a bomb damaged stage her leg went through a weak board; she severed the cartilage in her left knee and suffered a compound fracture in her right arm. The accident ended her dancing career.
In early 1946 Semenova returned to America and began her teaching career at the School of Dance Arts, Carnegie Hall, in New York City. Backed by a former USO contact, she formed American Youth Ballet in 1950 in Baton Rouge, Louisiana. In 1954, Semonova brought the American Youth Ballet to Houston. The following year, the newly formed Houston Foundation for Ballet invited her to form the Houston Ballet Academy - the precursor to the Houston Ballet. She remained director of the Academy for eleven years. Academy dancers also appeared in selected Houston Grand Opera performances.
In 1966, the Houston Ballet Academy Board of Directors pressed for a professional performing company under a new artistic director. Semonova declined an offer to continue as teacher and advisor. She resigned to form her own company, Ballet of Houston, which debuted in 1968. The company thrived through the middle 1980s. Despite increasing physical problems Semenova continued to teach privately in Houston until her death at the age of 76 on September 24, 1996. She is buried next to her mother, Olga Semenova, in the cemetery of St. Michael Island in Venice, Italy.
Scope and Contents
The Tatiana Semenova papers consist of seven boxes of personal material dating from 1933 to 1997. It documents Madame Semenova's early dancing career with the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, and her later teaching career in Baton Rouge and Houston. There are five series in this collection: Scrapbooks, Photographs, Personal, Programs, and Realia. The collection was received in no particular order. The processor has imposed the arrangement.
Subjects (Persons)
Semenova, Tatiana
Subjects (Organizations)
Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo; American Youth Ballet; Houston Ballet Academy; Houston Foundation for Ballet
Acquisition
Items in this collection were donated by Bette Fitzpatrick in the spring of 200l.
Detailed Description
- Scrapbooks (Box 1-3)
  This series consists of five personal scrapbooks of Tatiana Semenova. They contain programs, clippings, and photographs dating from 1933 through 1964. Many items are duplicated amongst the different scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbook (Ballet Russe and WWII), 1933-1945 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Baton Rouge, Louisiana), 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Spiral Binder (Baton Rouge, Louisiana), 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook (Houston, Texas), 1955-1964 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook (Houston, Texas), 1955-1964 (Box 3)
- Photographs (Box 4, Folder 1-30)
  This series consists of two boxes of photographs dating from the 1930s to the 1980s. The series has been broken into four sub-series: Publicity, Personal, American Youth Ballet, and Houston Foundation for Ballet. The ten folders of publicity photographs are of Tatiana, both alone and with others, and date from her early dancing career in the 1930s. The seven folders of Personal photographs date from the 1930s to 1950s. The seven folders containing American Youth Ballet photographs show her work with that group during the 1950s. The three folders of Houston Foundation for Ballet photographs are from the 1960s. Each sub-series is arranged chronologically.
  - Publicity Shots (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
    - Photographs, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Larger format photograph, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Photograph, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Photograph, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Photographs, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Photograph, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Photographs, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 11-19)
    - Photograph, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Photograph, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Print of a Russian man, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Inscribed photograph of John Frederick, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Photograph, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Inscribed photograph of Jean Delasser, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Photograph with her mother Olga, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Photographs of a sculpted bust of Semenova, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - American Youth Ballet (Box 4, Folder 20-27)
    - Photographs: Faust, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Photographs of workshop, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Photographs, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Photograph, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Photograph, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Photographs, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Group photograph, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Photographs: Circus,March 20, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Houston Foundation for Ballet (Box 4, Folder 28-30)
    - Photograph of Music Hall: Enigma,1959 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Photographs, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Photographs: Suite in White,1960s (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Personal Records (Box 5, Folder 1-17)
  This series consists of one box of personal records including naturalization papers, passports, driver's licenses, and death certificates. Unless otherwise specified, documents relate to Tatiana Seminova. Materials in this series date chronologically from 1944 to 1997.
  - Certificate of Naturalization, May 25, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Literacy, State of New York, Sept. 30, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Divorce Papers, May, June 1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Olga Semenova Papers, 1954-1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cremation Request, July 17, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Driver's Licenses and Passports, 1975-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Social Security Benefits and Personal List, Apr 5, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Durable Power of Attorney, Aug 22, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Obituary Houston Chronicle,Sept 25, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Death Certificate, Sept 27, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Funeral Papers, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Postcards of Tatiana's and Olga's Grave, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Cremation Papers, Mar 3, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - "Last Apartment" Letter, Nov 25 1997 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Address List for Memorial Cards, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Memorial Cards, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Inscribed Memories Book, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Programs / Leaflets (Box 6, Folder 1-22)
  This series consists of one box of ballet programs and leaflets dating chronologically from the 1950s to 1987. They follow Madame Semenova's career in New York, Baton Rouge, and Houston.
  - School of Dance Arts in New York, [1949] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Register of Baton Rouge, Feb. 18, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Programs: American Youth Ballet, 1953-54-55 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Houston Foundation for Ballet Charter, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Houston Foundation for Ballet Flyers, [1956] (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Program: Enigma, Feb. 23, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Esther Wolf presents Forty Six Paintings, 1960's (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Houston Foundation for Ballet sixth summer, June 5, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pan-American Round Tables of Texas, Apr. 1-5, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Program: Ballet Evening, Feb. 23, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Program: Die Fledermaus, Mar. 5 & 7, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Program: Sound and Motion, May 15-16, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - St. Anthony's Feast Day Annual Party Program, June 13, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Dance Magazine, Feb. 1964 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Saturday Review, Mar. 28, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Dance Magazine, May 1964 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Houston Post Sunday Magazine, October 11, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Houston Chronicle Texas Magazine, June 13, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Letter from Renzo Sommaruga, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Houston Ballet Press Kit for Tribute, Nov. 1983 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - News Clippings of Ballet Russe Tribute, Oct.-Nov. 1983 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Houston Ballet, The Nutcracker, Dec. 16-30, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Houston Downtown Magazine, Apri1 4, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Realia (Box 7)
  This series contains one Russian lacquer wood box, round with a three inch diameter, painted in gold and black.
  - Russian lacquer box, undated (Box 7)